Assured mission partner
collaboration is critical for
operational success.
Mattermost simplifies complex
operations through unified
workflows with
decision advantage.
This demo highlights how
federated workspaces,
external data feeds and
interoperability with matrix or
other legacy systems come
together in Mattermost.
With AI tools,
auto translation and
integrated Pexip video calls,
you'll see how decisions
are accelerated and mission
objectives are achieved.
Let's put this into action
with a simulated scenario.
Major Alex Reyes, an operations
officer at the joint forward
element is monitoring the Indo
Pacific theater for potential
threats and leading the
allied team's rapid response
coordination efforts.
In the intel watch channel,
which is governed by
attribute based access,
alerts begin to flow from ISR
analysts and cyber defense teams.
Airborne ISR collection over
Okinawa shows anomalies.
Additionally, cyber defense units
flag intrusion attempts targeting
SATCOM ground stations.
Behind the scenes,
external threat intelligence
systems enrich alert data using
tip and cue methods,
while Mattermost connects the teams
to act on the insights.
Once confirmed, key intelligence is
escalated with allies in the Indo Pacific
response ops shared channel.
Reyes posts a summary of the
threat indicators to initiate
the joint response,
and allied teams immediately
begin synthesizing context
rapidly aligning on a
coordinated course of action.
The Indo Pacific response ops
channel provides a synchronized
space where mission partners
coordinate securely across
organizational boundaries.
Each team retains control
of its own enclave,
but shared situational threads
flow seamlessly between partners.
Mattermost's auto
translation ensures fast,
accurate comprehension across
Japanese and English speaking teams.
As messages flow into
the shared channel,
Japan defense and joint forward
element personnel view native
language versions instantly,
preserving speed and clarity during
early stage threat coordination.
Major Reyes initiates the
multi domain threat response protocol
using a Mattermost playbook,
automating key coordination
steps across intelligence,
cyber and air
response functions.
Mattermost playbooks ensure
a structured response,
Standardizing workflows,
assigning roles and preserving
audit trails even under time
critical conditions.
Leaders convene securely
using the Mattermost Pexip
integration enabling sovereign
IL5 compliant video conferencing.
A live call is launched
directly from the Indo Pacific
response ops channel where ISR
imagery is reviewed in real time.
A forward deployed detachment
lead maintains critical
connectivity using a field kit
designed for degraded environments.
The expeditionary setup enables
mission critical updates to
flow through the shared
coordination channel,
ensuring real time alignment
with partner forces at Joint
Forward Element, Japan Defense,
and across the theater.
Major Reyes uses a
slash command to retrieve high
resolution imagery
from a drone asset.
A Japan defense analyst
overlays risk zones.
As allied teams rotate in
and out of the mission,
a partner analyst joins Indo
Pacific response ops mid operation.
Major Reyes uses Mattermost AI
agents backed with a sovereign
government grade LLM providing
the partner analyst with a
concise update on ISR trends
and task force actions so far.
With the ability to integrate
with systems like Matrix or XMPP,
partner forces leaders
remain situationally aware as
information flows across
partners who may still be
operating within legacy systems.
Here, we can see a Matrix room
synced with a shared channel in
Mattermost for allied comms.
From intel to action, every
task has been executed.
The response playbook is
complete and a final status
update thanks all partners for
securing the region together.
At the center of a
mission ready network,
Mattermost bridges
partners, platforms,
and intelligence to deliver
decision advantage in multi
domain operations, all grounded
in zero trust principles.
From signal to decision,
Mattermost keeps the mission in
motion.